A Guide to the Secretary of Finance, 1998-2001
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Secretary of Finance, 1998-2001
Library of Virginia
38947 and 38989
6.40 cubic feet.
Transferred from Secretary of Finance, 11 January 2002.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Privacy protected information closed for 100 years after date record created. Types of records restricted include, but are not limited to: federal and state income tax returns, W2s, death certificates, financial records and records with social security numbers that were sent to the Secretary of Finance and are part of the constituent correspondence series. Privacy protected material has been sealed but has not been removed from the collection.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Office of the Secretary of Finance on 11 January 2002.
Biographical/Historical Information
In 1970, the Governor's Management Commission Study recommended the creation of six "Deputy Governors" to assist the Chief Executive in his managerial duties, compatible functions of government were grouped under these administrative heads, who would serve as the Governor's top management team or "secretariats," as they are called now. The General Assembly in 1972 created six Secretariat positions initially. As government reorganized, that number fluctuated when government agencies expanded or consolidated.
Since the establishment of a secretarial system in 1972, there have been several reorganizations of that system. The financial management function of the state has shifted from under the direction of the Secretary of Finance to the Secretary of Administration; then to the Secretary of Finance and Administration and currently back to the Secretary of Finance, through various reorganizations of state government from the 1970s to the present. The function of the secretary is to provide sound fiscal management and recommend to the Governor a comprehensive budget for those agencies under his jurisdiction. The secretary's responsibilities are: to monitor programs, services and performance of subordinate state agencies, to develop state policies, programs for long-range service and policy formation; and approve solicitation or acceptance of any donations, gifts or grants; to hold agency heads accountable for their agency's administrative, fiscal and program performance. All secretaries are appointed by the governor and serve at his will.
Currently the Secretary of Finance is responsible for the direction or jurisdiction over the following state agencies and boards: Department of Accounts, Department of Planning and Budget, Department of Taxation, Department of Treasury, Treasury Board, Department of State Internal Auditor, Virginia Public Building Authority, Virginia College Building Board, Board of Commissioners of the Virginia Public School Authority and the State Council on Local Debt.
Governor George Allen appointed Ronald L. Tillett secretary in August 1996 following the resignation of Paul W. Timmrek. Governor James S. Gilmore III reappointed Tillett in January 1998. Tillett resigned in June 2001 and was replaced by his deputy, John W. Forbes. Forbes served until the end of the Gilmore administration.
Scope and Content Information
The records of the Secretary of Finance consist of correspondence and subject files relating to the fiscal management of state government (accession 38947) and constituent correspondence to the Governor referred to the secretary for response (accession 38989). The secretary's correspondence are arranged chronologically and consist of invitations, congratulatory notes to Tillett on his reappointment as Secretary of Finance, and letters to the editor in response to editorials or op-ed columns concerning fiscal issues including the car tax. Additional correspondence are arranged by department. The subject files are organized by headings. Notable topics include the car tax (Personal Property Tax Relief Act of 1998), queries from members of the General Assembly, Freedom of Information Act requests, briefing material for Governor-elect Mark Warner, presentations made by the secretary before the General Assembly's joint money committees, annual meetings with representatives of the major bond rating agencies and monthly revenue reports.
Constituent correspondence are arranged by tracking numbers assigned by the Governor's office and date received. Subjects included are taxation, budget concerns and suggestions, funding requests and complaints/requests for assistance in dealing with the Virginia Department of Taxation.
Arrangement
Accession 38947 arranged alphabtically by series name. Accession 38989 arranged numerically by constituent correspondence tracking number.
Contents List
- Appointment Calendars
  - Index of Speeches, 1998-2001 1998-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Car Tax - Correspondence and Press Releases, 1998-2001
  chronological
  - 26 January 1998 - 12 February 1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 18 February 1998 - 1 November 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 12 February 1999 - 23 February 2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Car Tax - Presentations, 1998-2000
  - 23 January 1998 - April 1998 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - June 1998 - July 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence - State Agencies, 1998-2001
  Arranged alphabetically by agency and chronologically therein.
  - Department of Planning and Budget (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Department of Internal Auditor (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Department of Taxation - Compliance Report (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Department of Treasury - General (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Department of Treasury - Bonds
    Arranged alphabetically by bond issuer.
    - Commonwealth Transportation Board (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - General Obligation Bonds (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - General Revenue Pledge Bonds (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Higher Educational Institutions Bonds (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Industrial Development Revenue Bonds (Virginia Advanced Shipbuilding and Carrier Integration Center) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Medical College of Hampton Roads (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Medical College of Virginia Hospitals (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Tax-Excempt Commercial Paper Program (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Virginia Biotechnology Research Park (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Virginia College Building Authority (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Virginia Housing Development Authority (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Virginia Public Building Authority (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Virginia Public School Authority (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Virginia Resources Authority (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Virginia Small Business Financing Authority, February 1998 - May 1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Virginia Small Business Financing Authority, October 1999 - March 2001 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Correspondence - Chronological, 1998-2001
  - 12 January 1998 - 22 April 1998 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 24 April 1998 - 11 August 1998 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 17 August 1998 - 29 December 1998 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 13 January 1999 - 20 April 1999 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 21 April 1999 - 23 August 1999 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 31 August 1999 - 28 December 1999 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 7 January 2000 - 4 May 2000 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 8 May 2000 - 16 August 2000 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 21 August 2000 - 20 October 2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - 23 October 2000 - 20 December 2000 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - 3 January 2001 - 30 April 2001 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 2 May 2001 - 10 December 2001 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Correspondence - Councils and Institutions
  - Virginia Executive Institute (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Business Council (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Correspondence - General Assembly, 1998-2001
  - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Financial Management Systems
  - Virginia Financial Systems: Report of Feasible Solutions (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Freedom of Information Act
  - FOIA Requests (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Governor's Transition Files, 2001
  - A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Transition Team (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and Transition Team (continued) (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - A Briefing for Governor-Elect Warner and the Transition Team (continued) (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Joint Money Committee Meetings, 1998-2001
  - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Rating Agency Files, 1998-2001
  - Articles (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Rating Agency Meeting, June 3-4, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rating Agency Meeting, June 9-10, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Rating Agency Meeting, June 26-27, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Rating Agency Meeting, October 17-19, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Revenue Reports
  - Fiscal Year 1998 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Fiscal Year 1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Fiscal Year 2000 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Fiscal Year 2001 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fiscal Year 2002 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Revenue Stablization Fund
  - Records (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Secretary of Finance - Strategic Plan
  - Copy of 1999 Strategic Plan (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Special Projects
  - Virginia Advanced Shipbuilding and Carrier Integration (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - National Air and Space Museum (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Year 2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Decentralization in Higher Education (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Decentralization in Higher Education (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Decentralization in Higher Education (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Decentralization in Higher Education - Reports (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Decentralization in Higher Education (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Tobacco Settlement Files, 1999-2000
  - Tobacco Securitization, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Tobacco Securitization, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Constituent Correpondence, 1998-2001
  Accession 38989 - Arranged numerically by correspondence number.
  - Correspondence Numbers, 161-1542 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 1543-3166 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 3303-9567 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 9658-12150 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 12156-15739 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 15865-16745 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 16817-17977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 18000-20584 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 20615-25256 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 25296-27418 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 25296-27418 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 27764-29994 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 30194-31858 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 31906-33707 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 33850-36249 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 36552-37192 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 37196-37923 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 37939-38328 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 38461-49732 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 49755-50732 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 50912-53208 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 53245-55393 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 55412-57043 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 57055-60320 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 60449-62587 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 65501-68644 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 68686-69496 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 69501-72155 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 72368-77417 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 77430-80536 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 80726-85443 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 85481-90929 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 91111-94932 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 95348-96420 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 96457-97726 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 97772-99254 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 99316-100830 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 100999-102642 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 102646-106308 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 106331-109820 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 109821-115345 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 115525-205472 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2004791-2026652 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2027483-2033675 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2033696-2037092 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2037093-2039116 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2039130-2044032 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2044363-2051942 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2051943-2058425 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2058430-2059202 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2059205-2060228 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2060253-2062393 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2062399-2064021 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2064039-2068424 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2068425-2072017 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2072060-2074348 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2074350-2075046 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2075227-2080507 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2080689-2084240 (Box 4a, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2084255-2086452 (Box 4a, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2086544-2087592 (Box 4a, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence Numbers, 2087593-2088728 (Box 4s, Folder 4)